Wadsworth Family Papers 1790-1950
Wadsworth Family Papers
1952-1964
Wadsworth Family
171 linear ft; approximately 50,000 items.
Milne Library at SUNY Geneseo
The Wadsworth Collections concern the first and continued settlement of land in the Genesee region known as the Phelps and Gorham Purchase. The collections consist of approximately 50,000 items from the land offices of the two branches of the Wadsworth family of Geneseo and cover the years 1790 to about 1950, with most dating from the 19th century. Business correspondence and ledgers, vouchers, deeds, maps and other business-related materials make up most of the collections. Milne's collection does not include official papers from the terms of Congressman James W. Wadsworth (1846-1926) or U.S. Senator James. W. Wadsworth, Jr. (1877-1952). The Library of Congress is home to The James Wadsworth Family Papers, a collection of personal and business materials which includes a large portion dealing with the Senator.
GB-0033-DCD
Important Information for Users of the Collection
Access
Access is restricted. Contact Special Collections Librarian to schedule an appointment
Acquisition Information
Acquired, 1976-1977. Gift of William P. Wadsworth (1976) and James J. Wadsworth (1977).
Overview
Jeremiah Wadsworth (1743-1804) of Hartford, Connecticut was one of the financiers of the American Revolution. At the end of the war, he, like many other contemporaries, bought land in Western New York State as an investment. His holdings lay mainly on the east bank of the Genesee River, between Geneseo and Rochester, in what was known as Phelps and Gorham's Purchase. Also, like many others, he did not occupy the land himself, but sent agents to administer or sell the holdings. In the case of Jeremiah, he convinced his two nephews, William Wadsworth (1761-1833) and James Wadsworth (1768-1844) to leave the comforts of Durham, Connecticut and settle in this wilderness. His persuasion was to offer them the chance to buy some of the choicest land at cost. In return, they were to oversee the sale of the rest of his holdings. William oversaw the development of the family farm, and James administered the land sales and leases.
William, who never married, was the sole year round resident in the first decade. James preferred to winter in more comfortable situations until after his marriage in 1804. At times he traveled in Europe, where he met and agreed to be agent for other landholders in the area, such as Sir William Pulteney from England and the Six family of the Hague. James' marriage produced three daughters and two sons. Daughter Elizabeth (1815-1851) was James' housekeeper and hostess for his guests after the death of his wife in 1831. In 1841, James divided his estate and responsibility for land management between his two sons, William Wolcott Wadsworth (1810-1852) and James Samuel Wadsworth (1807-1864).
This division of lands and responsibilities is reflected in the collection in important ways. James S. Wadsworth opened a land office at Number 1 Main Street to administer his part of the estate, and William Wolcott Wadsworth took over the Homestead office for management of his share of the holdings. When descendants of the two branches of the family gave the papers to Milne Library, it was stipulated that the papers should not be combined.
Books and registers that were originally found together in the Homestead Office in numerical sequence were separated, and researchers must use materials in both collections for continuity in some subject areas. The same situation applies to the Map Collection. Each office housed the maps that applied to its specific holdings. In the map case, there are two separate collections alphabetized by township name. It may be necessary to search both collections for the complete picture.
Three other events impacted the collection as it now stands. The first was the family decision to pack up most of the records from 1790 to 1838 and put them in storage. They have not been located by anyone in recent years, and may have been destroyed in one of the numerous barn fires that plagued the family from time to time. However, one important letter book remains from the second decade of the nineteenth century, and a collection of early family papers was given to the Library of Congress by the descendants of General James S. Wadsworth. These are available on microfilm in Milne Library. Orsamus Turner in his history of Phelps and Gorham's Purchase quotes from missing early records that he had read.
The other two events were the premature deaths of both of James Wadsworth's sons and heirs. William Wolcott died in 1851 after falling on ice. He left his wife Emmeline and two very young sons, William Austin Wadsworth (1847-1918), and Herbert Wadsworth (1851-1930) as heirs to his estate. Emmeline was not overly fond of living in Geneseo, and after her husband's death spent more and more time in Boston near her family and friends in the arts and letters. She was travelling in Europe when the Civil War broke out. She turned over all the business matter to clerks, housekeepers, and lawyers in Geneseo and Boston for almost twenty years.
General James S. Wadsworth was killed in the Civil War Battle of the Wilderness in 1864. His eldest son, James Wolcott Wadsworth was only 18, so the affairs at Number 1 Main Street were also administered by clerks and attorneys for some years. It may be helpful for one to remember that the proprietors of the Homestead were all named William after father James' death in 1844, and the proprietors at Number 1 Main street were all named James. There was only one brief exception. General James' son Craig Wharton Wadsworth (1841-1872) owned the Homestead for two year 1870-1871 but because of ill health, he sold it back to William Wolcott's son William Austin Wadsworth. William's mother Emmeline returned to Geneseo to live with him at the Homestead after it had been moved back from the street and remodeled around 1875.
Both William Wolcott and James S. Wadsworth had invested in extensive land holdings in Ohio and Michigan. Part of the correspondence concerns these lands and the agents who administered them. There are also photo albums containing pictures taken by Herbert's wife Martha Blow Wadsworth (1864-1934). Both branches of the family were involved in local, state and national politics. William Austin Wadsworth (1847-1918) was a friend and comrade in arms of Theodore Roosevelt and served him when he was Governor in Albany, but he would not leave Geneseo for Washington. His son William Perkins Wadsworth (1906-1982) also elected to remain in Geneseo and local politics. However, James Wolcott (1846-1926) was a Congressman; his son James Wolcott, Jr. (1877-1952) was a Senator; and his grandson James Jeremiah Wadsworth (1905-1984) was Ambassador to the United Nations.
The above is an overview of the collection. A more detailed description follows in the registers for various facets of the collection. If one wishes to read a further account of the Wadsworth family, see the chapter entitled "The Wadsworths of Geneseo" in Irene Beale's book Genesee Valley People. It is followed by a good bibliography of other sources.
- Maps
  Most of the Wadsworth maps are manuscript maps drawn by surveyors or copied from other originals for the use of the family. They are seldom dated, but internal evidence indicates that some date back to before 1800. This is especially true of the tract maps for both the Holland Purchase and the Phelps and Gorham Purchase. The names of settlers who leased or bought the lots has been written on most of the maps, and they are a good place to start a search for family residence in western New York. Following is a list of multiple or single lot maps by Township, Tract, County or Indian Reservation in the two collections.
  Avon
  Buffalo
  Buffalo Reservation
  Caledonia
  Caneadea Reservation
  Canadice
  Canawaugus Reservation
  Canisteo
  Catteraugus Reservation
  Charlotte
  Chenango County
  Chili
  Dansville, Steuben County
  Four Thousand Acre Tract
  Gates
  Genesee County
  Genesee River
  Geneseo
  Geneva
  Greece
  Groveland
  Hartford-See Avon
  Henrietta
  Holland Purchase
  Honeoye
  Hopewell
  Hornellsville
  Indian Lands
  Livingston County
  Livonia
  Mendon
  Military Tract
  Monroe County
  Morris Reserve
  Mt. Morris
  Naples
  Oakfield
  Ogden
  Ohio-set of county maps
  Oneida Reservation
  Ontario County
  Ossian
  Oswego
  Parma
  Penfield
  Perrinton
  Perry
  Phelps and Gorham's Purchase
  Phelps
  Pittsford
  Pulteney Estate
  Riga
  Rochester
  Rush
  Salina
  Seneca
  South Bristol
  Sparta
  Steuben County
  Tonawanda
  Tonawanda Reservation
  West Sparta
  Wheatland
  York
- Vouchers, 1838-1916
  Bills, Receipts, etc. from the Homestead Office
  - Core collection, 1838 -1917 (Box V1-V46)
    Office and Household Bills Organized by date
    The strength of this collection lies in the fact that it gives a picture of the tastes and life of one of the area's most important families over a century that spanned the time from frontier life to the industrial revolution and beyond. It is also a graphic illustration of the history of business printing and practices in the United States. As with the letters, more personal expenses gradually disappeared, perhaps because of the crises that the family experienced, or that they were not later kept by the office clerk. When Emmeline and son William Austin returned to live in the Homestead, personal vouchers were boxed separately.
  - Emmeline Austin Wadsworth:, 1870s (Box VEAW1-VEAW2)
    Organized by date and consisting of personal bills.
  - William Austin Wadsworth:, 1899-1916 (Box VWAW1)
    Organized by date.
- Land Contracts,Leases, and Sales, 1806-1912; Contracts before 1840 are few and far between. After 1840 leases were made for one year and were renewable. Land sales were registered at the County Court House. Some copies can be found in the Deed Books (See Deeds Section).
  Genealogists are often interested in proving that an ancestor was a tenant on a Wadsworth farm. Searching the core collection and other documents listed on the previous page can be tedious. There are in the first three contract boxes blue sheets that have the names of the tenants listed in calendars. Except for a very few leases as early as 1814, these records cover the 1830's and 1840's. Beginning in box C4 for 1852 and through and including the year 1860, there are folders entitle "Cash and Wheat Rents." These documents list the tenants and the farm or portion of farm which they rented in this decade.
  The tenants in all these guides are listed by townships, in the immediate Genesee Region. The majority of rented lands were in Avon. In the early years the Wadsworths issued long-term lease agreements. However, after 1838, most every lease is for one year. The family also allowed renters to pay part of their bill in wheat which they would deliver to a Wadsworth mill for credit. This was known as the "corn rent," a practice they learned about from friends in Scotland.
  - Core Collection, 1806-1912:; Arranged alphabetically by Town. (Box C1-C23)
    - Tenant farmers leasing Wadsworth lands in Avon, 1814-1851: (Box C1-C4)
      Tenant farmers leasing Wadsworth lands in Avon 1814-1851 Date is earliest date noted. See folders by year in Boxes C1-C4. For decade after 1851, see lists in "Cash and Wheat Rent" folders. Name given here is of first signator only.
      Albertson, D H 1845
      Albertson, Daniel 1845
      Bacon, Elisha 1845
      Baldwin, Thomas 1846
      Barber, Aaron 1845
      Barber, Jasper 1849
      Barnard, John 1845
      Benham, Reuben 1844
      Blackman, Spalding 1846
      Blake, John 1844
      Bone, James 1849
      Bow, James H 1850
      Bryan, Amasa 1851
      Buell, John 1836
      Burr, Warren 1844
      Butler, Hector 1848
      Butler, William 1847
      Chadwick, Josiah 1843
      Chandler, Lewis 1847
      Chapman, George 1850
      Chappell, Norman 1850
      Chase, David W 1844
      Comstock, Orville 1845
      Curtis, William 1850
      Cushing, William 1846
      Dann, John 1849
      Davis, George 1850
      Davis, Samuel 1848
      Davison, Norman 1814
      Deforest, Ezekiel 1844
      Douglas, Ambrose 1845
      Forsyth, Alexander 1814
      Fowler, Rodney 1839
      Fraser, John W 1844
      Fraser, William 1845
      Freeman, Jehial 1844
      Fridd, John 1845
      Galligan, Thomas 1844
      Hall, William E 1849
      Hamilton, James 1844
      Hamilton, John 1845
      Hawley, William 1850
      Hillman, David 1845
      Hogmire, William A 1851
      Hoskins, Alfred 1845
      Hosmer, James 1844
      Howie, Robert 1851
      Howit, Andrew 1846
      Howit, Audrey 1845
      Jerome, John 1847
      Hunter, Thomas 1851
      Jones, Richard 1851
      Kellogg, Amos 1839
      Kellogg, Nathaniel 1847
      Kellogg, Norman J 1848
      Keyes, S W 1844
      Kibbe, Charles E 1844
      Knowles, Paul 1842
      Lines, Jacob U 1844
      Lyman, Stephan 1814
      Marsh, Charles 1847
      Mather, Horatio N 1848
      Mitchell, Abel 1844
      Parsons, John 1841
      Peck, Archibald 1847
      Perkins, Dewitt C 1846
      Radford, William 1851
      Robinson, William S 1849
      Robinson, Zachariah 1845
      Seymour, Erastus 1845
      Shattuck, Kindall 1851
      Shepard, George 1815
      Sheldon, Enos 1851
      Smith, Josiah 1839
      Stone, Franklin 1844
      Story, Uriah 1844
      Story, William S 1846
      Tigh, Patrick 1844
      VanKleek, Jeremiah 1851
      Wattles, David 1842
      Weed, Joel 1815
      Winans, Ira and Theo 1844
    - Tenant farmers leasing Wadsworth lands in Geneseo, 1834-1851: (Box C1-C4)
      Tenant farmers leasing Wadsworth lands in Geneseo 1834-1851 See folders by year in Boxes C1-C4. Date given is earliest lease noted. For the ten years after 1851 see the lists of "Cash and Wheat Rents" in the boxes. Name given here is of first signator only.
      Austin, James 1840
      Austin, Russell 1845
      Barrows, Thomas 1844
      Bond, William H 1844
      Bryan, L Smith 1838
      Burgess, James M 1849
      Cartwright, Cyrus 1840
      Davis, Asron 1840
      Dunn, Christopher 1849
      Eaton, Joshua C 1839
      Elliot, William 1848
      Field, Leonard B 1839
      Field, R 1839
      Finley, Florus 1844
      Fowler, John B 1834
      Fowler, Rodney 1840
      Frid, George 1851
      Goodrich,Chauncey 1844
      Goodrich, Erastus C 1844
      Hathaway, Nadah 1840
      Hawley, James 1851
      Hill, Eli 1838
      Hogmire, Daniel H 1838
      Howard, A 1844
      Howard, Elmeren 1844
      Hutchinson, James 1837
      Joy, Benjamin 1838
      Kellogg, Amos 1838
      Langs, Jacob 1849
      Lauderdale, W E 1851
      Leonard, Ebenezer 1841
      Leonard, Samuel 1841
      Lewis, John 1839
      Lewis, Samuel 1851
      McLaren, Duncan 1844
      McLennen, Alexander 1845
      Miller, Allen 1842
      Munroe, John E 1842
      Murray, A J 1844
      Nowlen, Gurdon 1844
      Pfaff, Jacob 1851
      Raum, David 1841
      Roberson, Zachariah 1847
      Sage, Francis C 1845
      Shepard, David 1844
      Stafford, Henry 1847
      Stewart, Charles A 1840
      Swift, Samuel 1842
      Swift, Solomon 1838
      Swift, Zebulon 1839
      Tracy, Felix 1843
      Turner, Lyman 1850
      Tyler, Benjamin 1841
      Tyler, Thomas 1841
      Tyler, W 1841
      Weed, William 1835
      Wight, Smith 1842
      Winans, Theordore E 1843
      Worthington, A 1840
  - Geneva, New York, 1845-1897:; Organized by index. (Box CG1-CG2)
  - Michigan, 1863-1878:; Organized by area. (Box CM1-CM2)
  - Ohio, 1850s-1890s:; Arranged alphabetically by county, then by year under each county. (Box CO1-CO3)
  - Indian Lands, 1806-1912; Arranged alphabetically by Town (Box J106B)
  - Miscellaneous Contract Books, Contain information on leases and cash rents. Four of the volumes including contracts for Avon, Caledonia, Geneseo, Livonia, Rush, Ogden, etc.
- Deeds, 1792-1896; 15 volumes are on shelf 46, unwrapped or in boxes J46A, J46B, and J46C. Most are indexed. All copies are from County Court House records.
  Western New York originally was one county called Ontario from which land west of the river was split off into a Genesee County. About 1820, Ontario and Genesee were split into counties that we know today. Supposedly copies of deeds were given to each new county as it was formed for the lots that it contained. The Wadsworths found it convenient to have their own copies in the land offices.
  Below is a list of places where the Wadsworth family or their agents were named as grantors or grantees on deeds. All of the deeds should be registered in the appropriate County Court House, but in case one should wish to locate copies in this collection, one should refer to the two drawer card file for the box or book in which they are available. All the locations are in New York unless it is indicated otherwise.
  Alabama
  Batavia
  Bloomfield
  Brighton
  Bristol
  Caneadea
  Clarkson
  Dansville
  Erie County
  Fairfield
  Hume
  Sweden
  LeRoy
  Michigan (State)
  Mount Morris
  Ohio (State)
  Pembroke
  Royalton
  Shelby
  Short Tract
  - Fairfield (Ogden), 1802-1823; 13 (Box J46A)
  - Charles Six lands, 1817-1836; 14 (Box J46A)
  - Groveland, Mt. Morris, and Sparta, 1836-1845; 62; no index (Box J46A)
  - William Pulteney, 1810-1864; 15 (Box J46A)
  - Pulteney, Phelps, and Gorham, Before 1844; 44; Deeds and related records for Geneseo
  - James S and William Wolcott Wadsworth, 1844-1900; no number; Deeds and related records for Geneseo
  - James and James S. Wadsworth, 1792-1841; 45 (Box J46B)
  - James S. Wadsworth, 1841-1896; 76 (Box J76B)
  - Chili and Henrietta, no number; Indexed by grantor and grantee
  - Records of the Tonawanda and Buffalo Creek Indian lands, no number (Box J46C)
- Letters, 1837-1917
  - Core Collection, 1837-1917 (Box L1-L53)
    These letters concern the business and home life of the occupants of the Homestead at the south end of Main Street. Until the death of William Wolcott Wadsworth in 1852 they were more descriptive and anecdotal. After that the collection was kept up by the designated clerks and agents and contains fewer personal or family letters. The later letters refer mostly to business expenses. The first twenty boxes are provided with calendars for each folder. Of special interest to historians are Elizabeth Wadsworth's letters to her brother William Wolcott Wadsworth describing life in Geneseo while he was away from home. As mentioned above, letters before 1837 can be found on the microfilm from the Library of Congress. Also note the first letter book in the following section for 1815 to 1819.
  - Emmeline Austin Wadsworth letters, 1870s-1880s (Box LEAW1-LEAW3)
    Arranged by author with subjects including both personal and social content
  - William Austin Wadsworth letters, after 1870 (Box LWAW1-LWAW6)
  - Herbert Wadsworth letters, 1877-1879 (Box LHW1)
    Arranged by author
  - Wadsworth office clerks, agents and retainers in Geneseo, 1853-1917 (Box LMisc1-LMisc3)
    Arranged by name of employee then by date
  - Ohio and Michigan Agents:, 1850s-1870s (Box LO1-LO3)
    Arranged by agent
  - Senator James W. Wadsworth, Jr's Letters
    - (Box J109)
      Letters to his mother concerning school, college and army service.
    - (Box J111)
      Concerning Swift stock.
    - (Box J112A-J112K)
      Personal and business letters chronologically and by personal name.
- Letter Books, 1768-1864
  Letter books were the nineteenth century method for keeping copies of letters that one wrote to friends or for business matters. There was no carbon paper or photo copying device to duplicate and preserve such information. With some overlap and some gaps in coverage, the following books are in chronological order.
  - James Wadsworth, 1768-1844; 61 (Box LBK1)
    Letters from 1815 to 1819. Information about Merino sheep, the wool business, wheat, trade with Great Britain, the cold summer of 1816, and social issues (education, libraries, religion, newspapers) which interested James.
    Indexed
  - William Wolcott Wadsworth, 1810-1852; 58 (Box LBK1)
    Information about Ohio and Michigan land accounts.
  - James S. Wadsworth, 1807-1864; J. S. Wadsworth Letter Book. (Box LBK1)
    Letters from 1836 to 1842, Shelf 27. Information about family lands in Ohio and Michigan, the Treaty of 1838 with the Seneca Indians Chiefs concerning sale of Reservation lands in New York State and Indian emigration, and other family business.
  - William Wolcott Wadsworth Estate Letter Book., 1847-1863
    Concerning estate business matters.
    Separate index volume
  - Estate of James Wadsworth Letter Books., 1850-1863
    Kept by James S. Wadsworth and his clerk Edward R. Hammatt.
    - 1850-1855, Volume 1: 1850-1855
    - 1855-1863, Volume 2: 1855-1863
- Persons Who Worked for the Wadsworths as Farm or Day Laborers, 1831-1842; 5 ledgers
  One small book contains both a list and a ledger of accounts with workers. other books have a list at the beginning and then the managers diary of work assignments for the period, and one book was used as a payroll, the workers being asked to sign it every time they were payed for any work. The notes on work assignments are like a calendar and narrative of what happened on a Wadsworth farm.
  Farm labor did not usually live on the Wadsworth farms except on the flats, where there was for a time a dormitory and boarding house for single workers. The women who worked at the boarding house are also included in these lists. One very good reason for no housing for families on the flats was the annual flooding that occurred every year until the Mt. Morris Dam was built around 1950. Working men in the Genesee Valley lived in the villages and on high ground. They went out to work the farm land in the valley much as was the custom in Europe. Uninformed travelers, sometimes criticized the Wadsworths for practicing a form of peonage in this regard, when they saw no family housing on the flats.
  William Wadsworth (1761-183) was notorious for being a hard boss. When an acquaintance asked his brother James to take on a son and teach him farming, James discouraged the gentleman of any such notion, and advised him to send the boy elsewhere. William had died by the time these lists were made, but the farm managers, no doubt, carried on the work much as their former boss had done. His nephews William Wolcott and James S., who took over management of the farms in the following years, were praised by those who knew them for their enlightened and scientific farm practices. They were admirers of farm practices in Scotland and adopted some Scottish ways, such as "corn rent," payment with part of one's crop.
  - Farm Accounts and Hired Hands, 1831-1839:; 17 (Box AW1)
    Index of Names:
    Angell, Solomon
    Ayres, Burges
    Bailey, Thadeus
    Bailey, William
    Ballard, Elijah
    Barnes, George
    Bates, Solomon
    Beauman, Alfred
    Buckley, Elisha
    Butcher, John
    Canning, Hugh
    Clark, Joseph
    Cutler, William
    Diggen, John
    Drake, A.
    Drake, Leonard
    Eastman, James
    Garston, John
    Gregg, Robert
    Gregory, Elijah
    Hall, H.
    Hawley, Joseph
    Jacques, Jesse
    Johnson, James
    Johnson, William
    Lambert, William
    Linderman, Henry
    Linderman, James
    Lowry, Thomas
    Lucas, Peter
    McClary, James
    McCormick, Charles
    McKenzie, John
    McKinney, John
    McMurray, David
    McMurray, William
    Morton, John
    Odell
    Odle, Truman
    Parshall, Amos
    Press, William
    Price, Charles
    Quayle, John
    Robins, Aris
    Saxton, John
    Schramling, John
    Smith, Ira
    Swift, Lewis
    Taylor, Alvin
    Teneyck, Stephen
    Thomas, Griffith
    Traverse, I.
    Whitney, George
    Whitney, O.
    Wiggins, Caswell
    Williams, Amos
    Wyman, Jasper